Robert E. Lee Papers WLU.Coll.0064
Washington and Lee University, University Library Special Collections and Archives
- Non-correspondence by or from Robert E. Lee (Box 5-6)
  - Non-correspondence by or from Robert E. Lee (Box 5)
    - Lee's Newspaper Clipping Describing Death of Stonewall Jackson, 1866 (Box 5, Folder 36a)
      - Lee's Newspaper Clipping Describing Death of Stonewall Jackson, 1866; McGuire, Hunter, M.D. (Box 5, Folder 36a)
        This newspaper article is a clipping from an 1866 newspaper publishing the account of Thomas "Stonewall" Jackson's death during the American Civil War. The clipping was cut out and stored by Robert E. Lee during his tenure at Washington College. The original account comes from Jackson's former Medical Director Hunter McGuire who published it via the Medical College of Virginia.
    - Old Newspaper Presented to Library, 1866-09 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Old Newspaper Presented to Library, 1866-09; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 37)
        This note details the donation by Lee of a newspaper from 1800 to the library of Washington College.
    - Grade Report of W.C. Conner, 1866-10-31 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - Grade Report of W.C. Conner, 1866-10-31; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 38)
        This grade report from Washington College is signed by college president Robert E. Lee. The report is for the grades for college student W. C. Cooper for the term of October 31, 1866. The classes Cooper received grades for were Latin and Mathematics.
        Conner, W. C.
    - President's Reports, Typed Copies, 1866-1869 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - President's Report, 1866-06; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 39)
        This annual report is compiled by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College to the members of the Board of Trustees for the college. It details the population of preparatory student body and their statistics based upon state of origin, as well as their overall course performance. It goes on to evaluate the college's course offerings, facilities, and staff.
      - President's Report, 1867-06-19; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 39)
        This annual report is compiled by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College to the members of the Board of Trustees for the college for 1867. It details the population of total student body and their statistics based upon state of origin, as well as their overall course performance. It goes on to evaluate the college's course offerings, facilities, and staff.
      - President's Report, 1868-06-16; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 39)
        This annual report is compiled by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College to the members of the Board of Trustees for the college for 1868. It details the population of total student body and their statistics based upon state of origin, as well as their overall course performance. It goes on to evaluate the college's course offerings, facilities, and staff.
      - President's Report Copy 1, 1869-06-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 39)
        This copy of an annual report is compiled by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College to the members of the Board of Trustees for the college for 1869. It details the population of total student body and their statistics based upon state of origin, as well as their overall course performance. It goes on to evaluate the college's course offerings, facilities, and staff.
      - President's Report Copy 2, 1869-06-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 39)
        This copy of an annual report is compiled by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College to the members of the Board of Trustees for the college for 1869. It details the population of total student body and their statistics based upon state of origin, as well as their overall course performance. It goes on to evaluate the college's course offerings, facilities, and staff. This copy includes an additional note of names who whom copies of the report are to be sent.
    - Payments Authorized, 1866-1870 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to A. Alexander, 1866-11-19; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to S. Gilliam, 1866-06-08; Polk, James K. (James Knox); Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1866-10-17; Polk, James K. (James Knox); Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to Washington Society, 1866-10-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to William Edin, 1866-12-05; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to B. Mulligan, 1866-12-06; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to Natural Bridge, 1866-12-10; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to William Lough, 1867-08-06; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to, 1867-01-28; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1867-02-21; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Refund Authorized to G. R. C. Cinnamond, 1867-02-21; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to William E. Smith, 1867-03-15; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
        Smith, William E.
      - Payment Authorized to E. J. Heart, 1867-04-07; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to E. J. Heart, 1867-06-21; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to Henry S. Platt, 1867-10-24 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to E. L. Taylor, 1867-03-07; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to Henry W. Young, 1867-09-25; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1868-02-08; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1868-04-17; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to G. W. Varner, 1868-10-13; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to J. G. Worsham, 1868; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payments Authorized, 1865-11-15; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1866-03-15; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized, 1866-03; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Payment Authorized to Branding House, 1868-09-29; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Edmondson, James K., Colonel (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Paymens Authorized, 1870; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Donation Envelope, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Student Notices, Checks, Receipts, 1866-1870 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Check to Robert E. Lee from J. M. Leech, 1870-06-30; Leech, J. M.; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Bank of Lexington (Lexington, Va.) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Tuition Change Notice, 1867; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel
      - Withdrawal Notice for N. J. Kittrell, 1867; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Withdrawal Notice for C. C. Hearne, 1867-10-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Hearne, C. C.
      - Withdrawal Notice for John Swayne, 1869-03-16; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Swayne, John F
      - Refund Receipt for E. B., 1868-10-30; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Check to Robert E. Lee from J. M. Leech, 1870-01-27; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Leech, J. M.; Washington College (Lexington, Va.); Bank of Lexington (Lexington, Va.) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Withdrawal Notice for Joseph Sidle, 1867-03-01; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Leave of Absence Notice for J. W. Allison, 1869-02-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Donation Envelope for J.W. Allison Notice, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Withdrawal Notice for John C. J. Clay, 1866-03-12; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Clay, John C. J.
      - Withdrawal Notice for J. G. Castleman, 1867-10-16; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Castleman, J. G.
      - Lodging Notice for G. L. Owen, 1866-10-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Owen, G. L.
      - Tuition Receipt and Correction for James M. Grey, 1866-09-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Tuition Receipt and Correction for J. A. Mitchell, 1866-09-14; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
        Mitchell, J. A.; Edmondson, James K., Colonel
      - Withdrawal Notice for F. W. Armstrong, 1866-10-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - List of Materials Needed, 1865-1870; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Subscription Receipt to West and South, 1866-01-18; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Mailing Envelope, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Contract for Wood in Lee's Handwriting, 1867-05-13 (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Contract for Wood, 1887-05-13; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 42)
        In this letter of commission, Robert E. Lee during his tenure as president of Washington College lays out a contract for the supplying of wood to the college.
    - Memoirs of War in Southern Department and Sketch of Life of "Light Horse Harry", 1867-11-21 (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - Memoirs of War in Southern Department and Sketch of Life of "Light-Horse Harry" Lee, 1867-02-21; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 43)
        This is a manuscript of a the proposed biography of Robert E. Lee's father, Henry Lee III. The memoir documents various aspects of his life and his experiences. The memoir is hand written, but in an unknown hand. The content was likely dictated in some form by Robert E. Lee.
    - Memo Concerning Professor F. Preston's Death, 1869-11-23 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - Memorandum Book, 1869-11-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 44)
        This memo book begins with a memo from Robert E. Lee regarding the death of Washington College professor Frank Preston. It details his accomplishments, position, and plans for the memorial service. Frank Preston was a Greek professor from 1866-1869 with his death.
        The remainder of the memo book contains small notes in an unknown hand, along with several cut and removed pages. The notes appear to be pertaining to class material.
        Preston, Frank
    - Grade Report of W.S. Graves, 1868-02-08 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - Grade Report of W. S. Graves, 1868-02-08; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 45)
        This grade report contains the grades for Washington College student W. S. Graves for the session ending February 8, 1868. The report is filled out and signed by Robert E. Lee as president of the college. The classes includeded are Latin, Greek, German, and Mathematics. Graves recieved "distinguished" status in all courses.
        Graves, W. S.
    - Agreement with Richardson and Co. on Biography of Father, 1868-02-22 (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Agreement with Richardson and Co. on Biography of Father, 1868-02-22; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 46)
        This contract lays out the terms and conditions for Richardson & Co. of New York, NY to write, edit, and publish a biography on the life and experiences of Robert E. Lee's father, Henry "Light-Horse Harry" Lee III. The contract is written and signed by Robert E. Lee.
        Richardson & Co.; Lee, Henry
    - Notice to Students, Cadet Bell Funeral, 1868-03-04 (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - Funeral Notice, 1868-03-04; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 47)
        This notice was written by Robert E. Lee as president of Washington College. It is a public notice which was posted on March 4, 1868 canceling classes for the day and extending an invitation to "Cadet Bell's" funeral. Bell was a VMI cadet who had recently died.
    - Contract with Jedadiah Hotchkiss, 1868-06-29 (Box 5, Folder 48)
      - Contract with Jedadiah Hotchkiss, 1868-06-29; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 48)
        This contract details the agreement between the Washington College Survey Board and the renowned topographical surveyor Jedadiah Hotchkiss. It is a contract for Hotchkiss to perform various surveys on behalf of the Board of Survey to expand the college's map resources. The five year contract stipulates assorted restrictions on Hotchkiss's rights to the maps. It is signed by R.E. Lee on behalf of the Board of Survey.
        Hotchkiss, Jedediah
    - Paper Advocating Extension of Valley Railroad, 1869-04 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      - Paper Advocating Extension of Valley Railroad, 1869-04; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 49)
        In this paper, Robert E. Lee provides several reasons for the extension of the valley's railroad.
    - Lee Giving Permission for Frank McCutchan to be absent from College, 1869-12-23 (Box 5, Folder 50)
      - Lee Giving Permission for Frank McCutchan to be absent from College, 1869-12-23; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 50)
        This letter is from Robert E. Lee excusing Frank McCutchan from college from December 24th to December 29th.
        McCutchan, Frank, Rev.
    - Notice to Students on Christmas Holiday, 1869-12-24 (Box 5, Folder 51)
      - Notice to Students on Christmas Holiday, 1869-12-24; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 51)
        This notice written by Robert E. Lee was delivered for the Christmas holiday, stating that classes were suspended from December 25-27 in observance of Christmas. The notice goes on to wish that all students would observe and worship the holiday accordingly.
    - Observatory, 1870-01-15 (Box 5, Folder 52)
      - Observatory Funding, 1870-01-05; Edmondson, James K., Colonel; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 52)
        This is a proposal and sign-up list for donations for the creation of an astronomical observatory at Washington College. The donors include Robert E. Lee, James K. Edmondson, S. J. Campbell, James J. White, L. D. H. Ross, A. M. Glasgow, and William McLaughlin. Each donor made a pledge of $1000.
    - Southern Boundary Line of Virginia, 1870-02-24 (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Southern Boundary Line of Virginia, 1870-02-24; Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward) (Box 5, Folder 53)
        This printed report compiled by Robert E. Lee and the Washington College Board of Survey is addressing Gilbert C. Walker, the governor of Virginia. In the report, Lee explains the Survey Board's actions in surveying the southern borderline of Virginia for the first time in nearly 100 years. He goes on to explain the revelation of errors in the original survey and recommends that corrections be made accordingly.
    - Restoration of US Citizenship, 1975-01-14 (Box 5, Folder 54)
      - Restoration of US Citizenship, 1975-01-14 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Non-correspondence by or from Robert E. Lee (Box 6)
- Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1837-1870 (Box 7-12A)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1837-07-01-1866-01-31 (Box 7, Folder 1-35)
    - Control Folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondences, 1837-1864 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Haldimand S. Putnam to John L. Putnam, 1853-10-22 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        West Point cadet Putnam writes to his father regarding his his first semester at the academy. He mentions a number of officers including West Point Superintendent Robert E. Lee.
        Putnam, Haldibrand Sumner, 1836 - 1863; United States Military Academy
    - Correspondences, 1865-04-09 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Correspondences, 1865-04-14 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Correspondences, 1865-06-20-1865-07-28 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondences, 1865-08-02-1865-08-17 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Correspondences, 1865-10-13-1865-10-17 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Correspondences, 1865-10-18-1865-10-23 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Correspondences, 1865-10-24-1865-10-28 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Correspondences, 1865-10-29-1865-10-31 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-01-1865-11-5 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-07-1865-11-10 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-11-1865-11-14 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-15-1865-11-21 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-22-1865-11-27 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Correspondences, 1865-11-28-1865-11-30 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-01-1865-12-04 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-05-1865-12-09 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-10-1865-12-17 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-18-1865-12-23 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-25-1865-12-27 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Correspondences, 1865-12-29-1865-12-30 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Correspondences, 1866-01-01-1866-01-07 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Correspondences, 1866-01-08-1866-01-09 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Correspondences, 1866-01-10-1866-01-11 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Correspondences, 1866-01-12-1866-01-17 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Letters to and about Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01-1866-05-31 (Box 7A, Folder 36-63)
    - Correspondences, 1866-02-01-1866-02-03 (Box 7A, Folder 36)
      - William Archer Cocke to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01; Cocke, William Archer, Judge (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        William Archer Cocke wrote to Robert E. Lee February 1, 1866 from Monticello, Florida. He expresses the wishes of several youths in the Florida region to study at Washington College under Lee's leadership and requests a number of circulars on the college be sent to his address.
      - Laura G. Ogle to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01 (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        Laura G. Ogle wrote to Robert E. Lee from New Castle, Delaware on February 1, 1866. In the letter, she expressed her great admiration for Lee and her desire to emulate his example, despite societal pressures on her as a woman. She explains that her lifelong goal had become to meet and speak with Lee at some point. However, she explains that she has become and "invalid" and will remain so for her life, thus restricting herself to remaining in New Castle for the remainder of her life. She ends the letter with a request for a locke of Lee's hair.
      - Ralph Lete to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-01 (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        Ralph Lete wrote to Robert E. Lee on February 1, 1866 from Ironton, Ohio. He wrote to express his admiration for Lee, as well as to request a course catalog of Washington College for his son to potentially attend the school.
      - Jones Bros. & Co. to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-02; Jones Bros. & Co. Subscription Book Publishers (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        In this letter, Jones Bros. & Co. Subscription Book Publishers of Philadelphia, PA wrote a business letter to Robert E. Lee on February 2, 1866. In the letter, the company attempts to solicit their services to publish Lee's current writings on his Civil War Campaigns.
      - J. Temple to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-02; Temple, J. (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by J. Temple of Richmond, Virginia to Robert E. Lee on February 2, 1866. In the letter, Temple requests that Lee send him a number of circulars on Washington College for those in the area of Richmond who are interested in attending.
      - J. B. Williams to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-02; Williams, J. B. (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by J. B. Williams of Enfield, North Carolina to Robert E. Lee. He wrote to request a set of course catalogs for Washington College, and explains that he is recommending the school to his students.
      - W. W. Anderson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-02; Anderson, W. W. (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by W. W. Anderson of Bethany, West Virginia on February 2, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Anderson explains his dissatisfaction with the state of Bethany College. He requests that Lee, upon evaluation, accept himself and a dozen other Bethany College students into Washington College.
        Lee, Robert E., General (Robert Edward); Bethany College; Washington College (Lexington, Va.)
      - Robert H. Patterson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-03; Patterson, Robert H. (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by Robert H. Patterson of Abingdon, Virginia on February 3, 1866. Patterson wrote to request Lee send to him a catalog of Washington College as well as the Law School.
      - Joseph Finnegan to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-03; Finnegan, Joseph (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by Joseph Finnegan of Fenandina, Florida on February 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Finnegan explains to Lee that his friend, Captain Taylor, had recently passed away. He goes on to explain that Captain Taylor's two son's were currently attending Washington College. Finnegan continues to explain that the sons of Taylor are likely undisciplined due to their lack of quality education in their formative years. He requests that Lee offer them additional guidance in their situation.
      - William Parker Snow to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-03; Snow, William Parker (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by Captain William Parker Snow of Nyack, New York on February 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Snow explains his intense admiration for Lee and his leadership. He explains that he is in the process of authoring a monograph on the subject of southern generals during the Civil War. He goes on to express his patriotism for the United States in its current form and his admiration of Lee's willingness to fight for what he believed in.
      - C. B. Richardson to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-03; Richardson, C. B. (Box 7A, Folder 36)
        This letter was written by C. B. Richardson of New York, NY on February 3, 1866 to Robert E. Lee. In the letter, Richardson expresses his company's interest in Lee's experiences, and mentions an included copy of a book on the "Army of the Potomac" for Lee to examine. Richardson also requests a photograph of General Pendleton be sent with Lee's response.
      - M. Taylor to Robert E. Lee, 1866-02-03; Taylor, M. (Box 7A, Folder 36)